A Guide to the Norman R. Stoll papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA233
Rockefeller Archive Center
Norman R. Stoll papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1927-1976
Rockefeller Archive Center
Stoll, Norman Rudolph
Rockefeller University
FA233
2.5 Cubic Feet 4 boxes and 2 volumes.
4 boxes and 2 volumes.
Biographical/Historical note
Biographical Note
1892 Born September 4, North Tonawanda, New York
1910 Graduated Felton High School (class president)
1910-1911 Attended Syracuse University
1915 B.S. Mount Union College, Alliance, Ohio
1915 Editor THE DYNAMO (college weekly, jr. yr.)
1915 Editor THE UNONIAN (yearbook, sr. yr.)
1915-1917 Science teacher Massillino, Ohio High School
1918 M.S. University of Michigan, Graduate assistant in zoology
1918 2nd lieutenant (field artillery) World War I
1919-1921 Chairman, Dept. Biology Central High School and Junior College, Detroit (later Wayne University)
1923 Sc.D. Johns Hopkins University School of Hygiene and Public Health, Johns Hopkins University/Rockefeller Foundation, Joint Commission to Investigate Control of Hookworm Disease
1922 Puerto Rico
1923-1924 China - Associate in Parasitology, Peking Union Medical College
1926 Panama
1925-1926 Associate in Helminthology, Johns Hopkins University School of Hygiene and Public Health
1927-1950 Associate Member The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Dept. of Animal and Plant Pathology, Princeton, New Jersey
1941 D.Sc. (Honorary) Mount Union College
1943-1946 Lieutenant and Lt. Comdr. Parasitologist, Naval Medical Research Unit #2, Guam
1950-1962 Associate Member The Rockefeller University New York City
1962-1963 Professor (Member) The Rockefeller University
1963- Professor (Member) Emeritus, The Rockefeller University
1976 Died December 30, Princeton, New Jersey
1919 August 23 Married Estella M. Scott. Children: Henry Charles, Margaret E. Dawson, Louise M. Maddux.
1947 November 14 Estella Stoll died
1951 December 26 Married Helen Kennedy Stevens
Norman R. Stoll, 1892-1976, scientist at The Rockefeller University (earlier Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research) 1927-1976, whose work helped to advance the understanding and control of parasitic diseases especially in the detection and treatment of hookworm infection (free-living stages and measurements of the severity of the parasitism in man). From 1944-1967 he served on the International Commission for Zoological Nomenclature, serving as chairman of the Editorial Committee 1958-1961 when the revised code was adopted by the XV the International Congress of Zoology.
Editorships: Journal of Parasitology (1938-1943 Editor, 1944-1955 Editorial Board), Experimental Parasitology; 1951-1967 Editorial Board, International Code of Zoological Nomenclature; 1958-1961 Chairman of Editorial Committee; 1961 Code adopted by XVth International Congress of Zoology, Marquis Biographical Library Society 1969-
Member of: American Society of Naturalists, American Assoc. Advancement of Science (Fellow), Helminthological Society of Washington, American Society of Parasitologists (Charter Member); 1930-1932 Secretary-Treasurer; 1933-1957 Council Member; 1946 President; 1966 Emeritus, American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene 1960 C.F. Craig Lecturer, Royal Society of Medicine (Affiliate 1962-1969), Royal Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene, British Society of Parasitology (Charter Member), New York Academy of Sciences (Fellow), American Society of Zoologists, New York Society of Tropical Medicine (Charter Member); 1947 President; 1960 Life Member; 1962 Theobald Smith Memorial Lecturer
Other memberships: Ubiquiteers (Charter Member), Sigma Xi Rockefeller University Chapter, President 1958, Nassau Club, Princeton, Community War Service Committee (Chairman), Civilian Defense Council, Princeton Boro-Township 1942-1943, Board of Education, Princeton Township 1937-1944, Gamma Alpha, Phi Sigma, Delta Omega
Served on:
1944-1967 International Commission for Zoological Nomenclature
1952-1973 WHO Expert Advisory Panel on Parasitic Diseases
1961 Consultant in 7 African Countries
1955-1958 NSF Advisory Panel for Systematic Biology
1956-1957 Iran Foundation Medical Advisory Council
1957-1969 American Foundation for Tropical Medicine, Science Advisory Council.
1964-1969 American Foundation for Tropical Medicine, Liberian Institute. Co-principal investigator with Dr. H.C. Hsieh of endemic hookworm
1953 Copenhagen - International Congress of Zoology – Delegate
1958 London - International Congress of Zoology – Delegate
1963 Washington - International Congress of Zoology - Delegate
Honors
1969 Wisdom Hall of Fame
Scope and Contents note
Records, specimens, correspondence and records of work of the International Commission for Zoological Nomenclature.
Box 1: Biographical and autobiographical articles; bibliography; photographs; employment record correspondence. Box 2: Tapes and transcript of an oral interview; subject files Box 3: Background materials for "This Wormy World" Box 4: Three sets of records
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of Norman R. Stoll were deposited with the Rockefeller University Archives on March 4, 1977 by Margaret Stoll Dawson, daughter.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 St68
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Medical sciences; Biochemistry; Medicine, Preventive; Zoology; Diseases; Parasitology; Medical research; Hookworm disease; Life sciences; Biology -- Research; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; International Commission on Zoological Nomenclature
- Employment record (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Biographical articles as prepared for RU (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Handwritten note which appears to be seminal idea on concept of "self-cure" (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Portion of letter on 25th anniversary of graduation from Mount Union, 1940 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1947 Holiday Greetings from Leyte Correspondence on Naval Reserve retirement (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Medical reports (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letter of Greetings written to those from Navy associations who jointly sent 80th birthday greetings, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bibliography prepared by NR Stoll (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bibliography prepared in Archives Office as a Table of Contents for 2 volumes "Collected Reprints" (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Norman Rudolph Stoll: Scientist, Teacher, Friend" an appreciation prepared by Malcol S. Ferguson and published in EXPERIMENTAL PARASITOLOGY 1+1, 1977; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence on retirement allowance (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Obituary clippings (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Administrative correspondence, 1956-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  Scope and Contents note
  Mainly notices from various departments.
- Administrative correspondence, 1926-1974; 1½ inch file (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Record of Dr. Stoll's long association with The Rockefeller University. Included are several long and informative letters from trips abroad: England, Liberia, Vienna.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  Placed in the RU Archives from the Office of Faculty Records.
- Photographs of NR Stoll (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Includes 1 wedding photo of daughter.
- Photographs of Princeton (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Includes group photos of workers in the Princeton labs as well as photos of construction and buildings.
- Reports and references not dated not clear (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Record of RU staff meetings, 1933-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Some correspondence when NR Stoll served on committee.
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Group from 1961 trip.
  R.W. Glaser.
  T.M. Rivers.
  W.A.S. Raghawan (sp?)
- Assorted and scattered items, 1933-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence L.A. Taffs Visiting investigator, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Oral interview on the closing of the Princeton laboratories, made in Spring-Fall 1972; 3 tapes (both sides) and typescript which Dr. Stoll never decided to edit. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
  This was done in part by dictation and partly on an interview.
- 2 publications on hookworm, 1914 1928 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- War Department Publication on DDT and insecticides, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- War department manual on DDT, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- v. 1, no. 2 Journal of Military Medicine in the Pacific (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Assorted biographical notes of RIMR staff (published) (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Record of experiments performed, 1949-1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Assorted handwritten notes applicability not always clear, 1952-1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Iran Foundation, 1951-1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Some correspondence and Annual Report 1957/1958.
- JOURNAL OF PARASITOLOGY, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Correspondence with Justus F. Mueller, editor and draft of a short history of The American Society of Parasitologists; some editorial reports.
- 2nd International Congress of Parasitology, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Includes Colloquium on The Cultivation of Helminths.
- Articles and papers not all listed in, bibliography "First annual meeting of the American Society of Parasitologists. 1925" reprint from Journal of Parasitology 12 (1926), 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Stoll, N.R. "What can be done about hookworm?" 7th International Congress on Tropical Medicine and Malaria. Proceedings (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Announcement of FIRTST NORMAN R. STOLL LECTURE (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Typescript: "The stream of scientific publication (in parasitology): Does it have a problem of pollution? of Eutrophication? (2 cop.) 2nd International Congress of Parasitology (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Typescript: Establishment of three strains of ENTAMOEBA INVADENS in media without tissue (Box 2, Folder 9)
- The First Twenty Years of the New York Society of Tropical Medicine (Stoll on committee) (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Duplicated copy of "Endemic Hookworm in Liberia" (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Reprint from TAXON 1960 meeting of Editorial Committee of International Code of Botanical-Nomenclature (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Remarks at the Dedication of the W.W. Cort Library (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Handwritten listing by NRS of dates and publications he considered important landmarks in career (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Stoll, N.R. "Midstream" reprinted from Mount Union College Bulletin, 1940 July (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Stoll, N.R. "This Wormy World" JOURNAL OF PARASITOLOGY, 33 (1947) (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Stoll, N.R. The Osmosis of research: ... Bulletin of New York Academy of Medicine 48 (1972) (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Stoll, N.R. Rudolf William Glaser and Neoplectana EXPERIMENTAL PARASITOLOGY 33, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Stoll, N.R. "Mankind of the future", Duplicated copy (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "This Wormy World" - address given in Dec. 1946 and published in JOURNAL OF PARASITOLOGY Feb. 1947 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  Said to be "the most widely published and quoted publication in helminthological parasitology since the War". Folders 1-5 consist of background; data sheets; manuscript; reprint and reviews.
- Unidentified film (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Appears to be a European trip.
- Three groups of data sheets, 12½ × 5 × 8½ (Box 4)
  - THIS WORMY WORLD. Arranged geographically according to reprint request location (Box 4)
  - Inactive list of reprints sent (Box 4)
  - Duplicated file and record of mss no. 1-622 submitted to JOURNAL OF PARASITOLOGY and publication decision (Box 4)
- "Collected Reprints", 2 volumes
  Processing Information note
  Relocated to RAC library 8/9/1988